Guide to the Lesbian Health Resource Center Records, 1987-2005 RL.00812
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lesbian Health Resource Center records
1987-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lesbian Health Resource Center
RL.00812
4.5 Linear Feet
Durham-based community organization that provided health advice and workshops for lesbians. Successor to the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project, founded in 1982. The LHRC opened in 1996. Collection includes administrative materials, grant and funding applications, volunteer orientation agendas, and a resource library maintained by the LHRC during the 1990s. Topics include mental and physical health for lesbians, in particular HIV/AIDS prevention, breast cancer prevention and screenings, and safe sex practices. Also includes materials about the LHRC's plans for a Lesbian Health Clinic in North Carolina, its ongoing relationships with other community organizations, and workshop materials on feminism, health, and leadership. Membership and participation lists are closed until 2030. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
3375 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Membership and participation lists are closed until 2030.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lesbian Health Resource Center Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2011.
Historical Note
The LHRC was a nonprofit organization founded in 1996 to provide educational workshops and resource materials on all health issues for women who partner with women. It was the successor organization to the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project, whose records the Sallie Bingham Center also holds. The NCLGHP was founded in 1982 to combat homophobia in existing health care institutions, and to provide gay men and lesbians the means to assume control over their own health care.
Collection Overview
The records of the LHRC are in many was a continuation of the records from the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project, also held by the Bingham Center. Early materials frequently reference or were created by NCLGHP members, and there are also overlapping interests with some resources for gay men, despite the fact that the majority of the materials are targeted towards the lesbian community and their activities in the Triangle.
The grant materials and other financial files that make up the first series include applications, correspondence, and general information about the budget of the LHRC and the grants that it sought for programs and operations. Also included in this series are materials from the 501(c)3 application, as well as some correspondence from the IRS regarding the organization's tax status.
The LHRC's Lesbian Health Clinic files detail the planning and fundraising by the organization in preparation for opening the LHC. This series includes correspondence, steering committee minutes, handouts from different fundraising and awareness events, and other notes and research about healthcare and the operation of a health clinic.
The collection's subject files are largely drawn from the LHRC Resource Library, which was maintained by the LHRC for use by its members. Topics include healthcare, particularly women's health and lesbian health; cancer, especially breast cancer; AIDS and the spread of HIV; safe sex; domestic violence; parenting; homophobia, especially within the medical community; and other topics like health reading materials or other resources.
Some of the LHRC's activities and events are documented in the fourth series, including information and planning materials from the NCGLHP's participation in the Breast Cancer Leadership Summit and subsequent breast cancer awareness events in the early 1990s. Other activities represented include North Carolina Pride Days, breastcasting, a lesbian sex group, and general healthcare workshops.
Finally, the administrative files relate to the running of the LHRC, including everything from document masters for letterhead and logos to the volunteer orientation materials from orientations as late as 2005. Also includes some information from partner organizations, including the Mautner Project, Lesbian Avengers, and local community organizations including Triange Community Works. Related to this series is the Oversize Materials series, which consists of two document masters for posters promoting awareness about breast cancer and AIDS in the lesbian community.
The Restricted series is actually just one box of material, mainly membership and participation lists, which is closed until 2030.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Related Material
The LHRC was the successor to the North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project, whose records are also held by the Bingham Center.
AIDS (Disease) -- Prevention; Lesbians -- North Carolina -- Durham; Breast -- Cancer -- Prevention; AIDS (Disease) -- Medical care; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; Lesbians -- Mental health; Sexually transmitted diseases; Lesbians -- Health and hygiene; Lesbian mothers; Sex instruction for lesbians; Breast -- Cancer -- Lesbians; Lesbian partner abuse; North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project; Lesbian Health Resource Center; Lesbian Health Resource Center; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Fundraising and Financial files, 1991-2005, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Grant applications, internal financial files, and copies of the LHRC's 501(c)3 application to the IRS.
  - Bylaws, Mission Statement, Board of Directors, 1998-2001 (Box 1)
  - LRC meeting minutes, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Budgets and activites outlines (Box 1)
  - IRS tax status, 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Grants
    - Lucius and Eva Eastman Fund, 1991 (Box 1)
    - A.J. Fletcher Foundation, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Resist, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Mary Reynolds Babcock, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Bryan Family Foundation, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kate B. Reynolds, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Out Fund, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Z. Smith Reynolds, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Tides Foundation, 1994 (Box 1)
    - New World Foundation, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Grants, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
    - Various grant information (Box 1)
    - Triangle Community Foundation, 1995-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Race for the Cure, 1998-1999, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - ART-Women's Health Initiative, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Potential funding opportunities, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Chicago Resource Center, 2000, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - FSC Grant, 2001 (Box 1)
    - FEX grant information, 2002 (Box 1)
    - NABCO-Within Our Reach, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Funders for Lesbian and Gay issues, 2002 (Box 1)
  - 501(c)3 IRS application, 2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Audit reports, 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Grant Information (Box 6)
- Lesbian Health Clinic materials, 1994-2001, 2 boxes
  Notes, correspondence, flyers, resources, and research regarding the LHRC's efforts to open a Lesbian Health Clinic serving Triange (NC) women. Includes information about other successful clinics, common health problems and concerns faced by lesbian patients, and internal correspondence regarding their efforts to raise funds.
  - Steering Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising notes, 1995 (Box 1)
  - History/past workshops, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Meetings, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Past LHC stuff, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Health resources/printouts, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Resources, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Research on building the clinic, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lesbian health (Box 1)
  - Notes, fliers, etc. (Box 1)
  - Office Supplies (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2001 and undated (Box 6)
  - Stickers (Box 6)
- Subject Files, 2 boxes
  Most of these materials appear to have been part of the LHRC's Resource Library.
  - Abortion (Box 2)
  - Aging/Long Term Care (Box 2)
  - AIDS/HIV, including prevention, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Battered women (Box 2)
  - Bisexuality (Box 2)
  - Book titles (Box 2)
  - Cancer (general) (Box 2)
  - Cancer, Breast and Cervical, including screenings, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Cancer, Ovarian (Box 2)
  - Childbirth/parenting (Box 2)
  - Clinic research (Box 2)
  - LGBT Conferences (Box 2)
  - Culturally Competent Care trainers manual (Box 2)
  - Domestic violence (Box 2)
  - General information, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Greenpeace (Box 2)
  - Hate crimes/Gay bashing (Box 2)
  - Health
    - Healthcare, Access to (Box 2)
    - Lesbian health bibliographies (Box 2)
    - Lesbian health reports and studies (Box 2)
    - Lesbian healthcare issues (Box 2)
    - Lesbian healthcare surveys, 1988 and undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Lesbian healthcare surveys, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Fact sheets on women's health issues (Box 3)
    - Women's health issues: planning for diversity (Box 3)
    - Lesbian/women's health organizations (Box 3)
    - Women's health pamphlets and resources from outside organizations (Box 3)
    - Lesbian health-Research (Box 3)
    - Lesbian health resources order forms (Box 3)
    - Quality Healthcare for All Clients and All Female Clients powerpoints (Box 3)
  - Lesbian Health Reading Group: Current Readings (Box 3)
  - Homophobia in healthcare, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Legal issues (Box 3)
  - Menopause (Box 3)
  - Mental health/social issues (Box 3)
  - Lesbian parenting articles and resources, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Resources for gays, lesbians, and bisexuals in the Triangle (NC) (Box 3)
  - Sex, including safe sex (Box 3)
  - Stress, stress management, and relaxation (Box 3)
  - Substance use and abuse (Box 3)
  - Women studies (Box 3)
- Center activities and events, 1993-2000, 3 boxes
  Includes materials on LHRC events and other community events attended or supported by LHRC members, including the North Carolina summit on breast cancer in 1994 and the North Carolina Gay Pride events from the late 1990s.
  - Breast Cancer Leadership Summit, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Breast Cancer Coalition and North Carolina mini-summit, 1994 and undated (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Breast and Cervical Cancer Control Program (NCBCCCP), 1994 and undated (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Lesbian Health Conference (Box 3)
  - NC Prides, 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Health workshops, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Domestic Violence Beacon Program, UNC, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - LHRC workshops, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - LHRC Activities and Events Calendar, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Body and Soul, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Pride Party, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Health workshops, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Breast casting, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Questions from Lesbian Sex Group box, late 1990s (Box 4)
  - Adolescent health, April 2000 (Box 4)
  - Workshop: How to Facilitate Workshops, May 2000 (Box 4)
  - LHRC/Pride office orientation, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Volunteer Orientation, 2000-2001 (Box 6)
  - How to Facilitate Workshops, 2000 Feb. 25 (Box 6)
  - Pride, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Pride, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Pride, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Breast Casting Donor Tickets (Box 6)
  - Event Flyers (Box 6)
- Administrative files, 1994-2005, 2 boxes
  Office materials, resources, and volunteer orientation files from the operation of LHRC. Includes master documents of forms and worksheets; program information for the various orientations and meetings; materials from other community organizations such as the Mautner Project, GLSEN, APPLES, and Triangle Community Works!; and other miscellaneous materials.
  Collection's electronic media, consisting of 3.5" floppy disks, has been removed to Duke's Electronic Records server. contact the Rubenstein Library if you are interested in accessing this material.
  - Blank workshop/tabling logs (Box 4)
  - Tabling logs (Box 4)
  - Brochure masters (Box 4)
  - LHC tables master copies (Box 4)
  - LHRC in the news (Box 4)
  - LHRC newsletters (Box 4)
  - LHC event flyers (Box 4)
  - LHRC handouts (Box 4)
  - Lesbian Resource Binder: "Helpful Info for Lesbians" (Box 4)
  - Incoming correspondence from other health organizations, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Pro-woman organization mailings, handouts, and newsletters, 1993-1997 and undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project materials (Box 4)
  - Organizations for gay men in the Triangle (NC) (Box 4)
  - Lesbian Avengers promotional materials (Box 4)
  - Mautner Project resources, pamphlets, and handouts (Box 4)
  - Mautner Project newsletters, 1994-2002 (Box 4)
  - GLSEN mailings (Box 4)
  - Triangle Community Works! mailings, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - APPLES mailings, 2002 (Box 4)
  - T-Rag (Box 4)
  - Catalogs (Box 4)
  - Withdrawn electronic media (Box 4)
  - Office notes, 2002 and undated (Box 4)
  - Blank database forms (Box 4)
  - Maps, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Printer (Box 4)
  - Calls received, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - Phone log (Box 4)
  - LHRC Library Catalog, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Provider Questionnaires (Box 4)
  - Tabling log (Box 4)
  - Letterhead and labels (Box 4)
  - Workshop surveys (Box 4)
  - Pro-Lesbian magnets (5 LHRC magnets) (Box 4)
  - Web info, ISP (Box 4)
  - LHRC logo (Box 4)
  - Correspondence re: State Employees Combined Campaign money, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Finances, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Requisitions/refund forms (Box 4)
  - Orders (Box 4)
  - Non-profit info (Box 4)
  - Insurance info (Box 4)
  - Organizational/non-profit resources (Box 4)
  - Self-help ventures lease, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Interns-UNC, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Volunteer orientations
    - 1999 January 30 (Box 4)
    - 1999 June 29 (Box 4)
    - 1999 September 11 (Box 4)
    - 1999 October 23 (Box 4)
    - 2000 April 1 (Box 4)
    - 2000 June 24 (Box 4)
    - 2000 September 21 (Box 4)
    - 2001 April 5 (Box 4)
    - Materials lists (Box 4)
    - 2001 June 19 (Box 4)
    - 2001 October 11 (Box 4)
    - 2005 January 15 (Box 4)
  - Committee Meeting Feedback, 2001 May 9 (Box 6)
  - Community Works (Box 6)
  - Duke University (Box 6)
  - Durham County Women's Commission, 2001-2002 (Box 6)
  - GLSEN Triangle (Box 6)
  - Indigenous Peoples' Task Force (Box 6)
  - Informative flyers and brochures (Box 6)
  - Lesbian Avengers (Box 6)
  - Lesbian-Friendly Healthcare Providers (Box 6)
  - Lesbian Health News (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous writings and records (Box 6)
  - National Lesbian Healthcare Survey NLGHF, 1988 (Box 6)
  - NCLYN (Box 6)
  - The Newsletter (Box 6)
  - Photograph, 2000 Nov. 1 (Box 6)
  - Rape Crisis of Durham, 2000-2001 (Box 6)
  - Timeline, 1996-2000 (Box 6)
  - Triangle Families (Box 6)
  - Triangle Rag, 2000 Jan. (Box 6)
  - University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (Box 6)
  - Volunteer Recruitment (Box 6)
  - Women's Center (Box 6)
- Oversize Materials, 2 folders
  Nine posters of varying sizes.
  - Breast cancer (Oversize-folder 1)
    "As many as 1 in 3 lesbians may be diagnosed with breast cancer. For more information, call: North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project..."
  - AIDS (Oversize-folder 1)
    "Our sons, our daughters, our sisters, our brothers, our parents, our lovers are dying. For more information call: North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project..."
  - Matters of the Heart (Oversize-folder 2)
    "In matters of the heart, nothing is true except the improbable. -Madame de Stäel"
  - LHC (Oversize-folder 2)
    Stiff, felt poster featuring Lesbian Health Center name and logo.
  - Choice (Oversize-folder 2)
    "I will choose what enters me, what becomes flesh of my flesh... -Marge Piercy" with Roxanna Bikadoroff drawing.
  - Diversity (Oversize-folder 2)
    "Celebrate community. Honor diversity. Communities teach tolerance, co-existence and mutual respect... -Karen Kerney and Scott Russell Sanders."
  - AIDS and Breast Cancer (Oversize-folder 2)
    "Pray for the dead and fight like hell for the living. -Mother Jones (1830-1930) Historically, the United States Government has maintained a greater commitment to absurd and excessive military spending..."
  - "Her" Erection (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Breast Cancer (Oversize-folder 2)
    "As many as 1 in 3 lesbians may be diagnosed with breast cancer. For more information, call: North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Health Project..." Duplicate
- RESTRICTED Materials, 3 boxes
  Membership lists and other participation information is closed until 2030.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  CLOSED: Material closed to use until 2030.
  - Membership lists and files (Box 5)
  - Participation lists for workshops, etc. (Box 5)
  - 2 t-shirts (Box 5)
  - 2 rolodexes with contact information (Box 5)
  - Financial records, 1994-1998, 10 folders (Box 7)
  - Mailing lists (Box 7)
  - Participant and volunteer sign-up sheets (Box 7)
  - Phone logs, 1998-2002, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Phone log statistics (Box 8)